Guide to the Harvey Weiss Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Harvey Weiss papers
1955-2007
GEN MSS 992
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
25.6
(95 boxes) + 1 roll
The collection consists primarily of artwork and storyboards for books authored and illustrated by Harvey Weiss, as well as correspondence, clippings, printed material, photographs and other material relating to various book projects and several illustrated journals. The collection documents Harvey Weiss's career as a children's illustrator and author, and his process of researching, writing and illustrating books.
Weiss, Harvey, 1922-
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from the Estate of Harvey Weiss on the Jockey Hollow Fund, 2008.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Harvey Weiss (1922-2007)
Harvey Weiss was an illustrator and author of children's books. His works include the eleven-volume "Beginning Artists Library" series, including titles such as Clay, Wood, and Wire: A How-to-Do-It Book of Sculpture (1956), Pencil, Pen and Brush Drawings for Beginners (1961), and Ceramics: From Clay to Kiln (1966). His other books include How to Be an Inventor (1980), Machines and How They Work (1983), and Maps: Getting From Here to There (1991). He also illustrated books by Miriam Schlein, to whom he was once married, and Joan M. Lexau, among other authors.
Weiss was a noted sculptor, and his sculptures form part of many private and public collections. He was also a professor of sculpture at Adelphi University.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists primarily of artwork and storyboards for books authored and illustrated by Harvey Weiss, as well as correspondence, clippings, printed material, photographs and other material relating to various book projects and several illustrated journals. The collection documents Harvey Weiss's career as a children's illustrator and author, and his process of researching, writing and illustrating books.
Arrangement
Organized into eight series: I. Writing and Research Files. II. Book Proofs and Related Material. III. Illustrated Journals. IV. Correspondence. V. Other Papers. VI. Photographs. VII. Printed Material. VIII. Book Art, Storyboards, and Oversize Photographs.
While the series arrangement reflects, as far as possible, an intellectual arrangement of material, the bulk of the material is oversize and is therefore physically arranged by size. As a result, the box numbers are not contiguous and material within each series overlaps with and/or relates to material found in other series. In order to locate all relevant material within this collection, researchers will need to consult each series described in the Collection Contents section.
Authors, American -- 20th Century -- Archives; Authors, American -- Juvenile literature; Children's literature, American -- 20th Century; Children's stories, American; Illustration of books -- United States; Illustrators, American -- 20th Century -- Archives; Picture books for children -- United States; Illustrations (layout features); Photographs; Weiss, Harvey, 1922-
- Writing and Research Files, Series I
  - "3D, 2D, 1D" (Box 1)
  - "The Age of Steam" (Box 1)
  - "Awful Things I've Done" (Box 1)
  - "Cartoons and Cartooning" (Box 1)
  - "Carving - An Intro to Wood and Stone Carving", 2 (Box 1)
  - "The Gadget Book" (Box 1)
  - "Games and Puzzles you can make yourself", 2 (Box 1)
  - "Hammer and Saw" (Box 1)
  - "How I Built the Artificial Chicken" (Box 1)
  - "How to be an Inventor" (Box 1)
  - "How to Make Books" (Box 1)
  - "How to Make Movies", 3 (Box 1)
  - "How to Run a Railroad - everything you need to know about Model Trains", 3 (Box 1)
  - "Introduction to Ceramics" (Box 1)
  - "Maps: Getting from Here to There" (Box 1)
  - "Maps: Getting from Here to There", 8 (Box 2)
  - "Model Buildings and How to Make Them," dummy, circa 1978 (Box 2)
  - "Media X" (Box 2)
  - "Museum of your Own," typescript, 2 (Box 2)
  - "Paint, Brush and Palette - Intro to Painting" (Box 2)
  - "Paul's Horse Herman" (Box 2)
  - "Pete" (Box 2)
  - "Shelters - from Teepees to Igloos", 4 (Box 2)
  - "Ship Models and How to Build Them" (Box 2)
  - "Strange and Wonderful Aircraft", 10 (Box 2)
  - "Sooner Hound" (Box 7)
  - "Submarines and Other Underwater Craft", 10 (Box 3)
  - "Tall Tales" (Box 3)
  - "What Holds it Together", circa 1977; 5 (Box 3)
  - "Wheels, Wood and Feathers - 23 Fanciful Products" (Box 3)
  - "Working with Cardboard and Paper", 2 (Box 3)
  - "Working with Cardboard and Paper," photographs (Box 13)
  - "Working with Wood" (Box 3)
  - Research Material (Box 3)
    - "Let's Make a Lion" (Box 3)
    - "Pencil, Pen and Brush" (Box 3)
    - Photography (Box 3)
    - Photocopies for Research (Box 3)
- Book Proofs and Other Book Material, Series II
  - "Bernadine and the Water Bucket", circa 1966 (Box 4)
  - "The Big Cleanup", circa 1967 (Box 4)
  - "Cartoons and Cartooning," book jacket, 1990s (Box 4)
  - "Collage and Construction" (Box 4)
  - "The Gadget Book," book jacket, circa 1971 (Box 4)
  - "Games and Puzzles you can Make Yourself", book proof, circa 1976 (Box 4)
  - "Harvey Weiss - Paul Rosenberg and Co.", exhibition catalog, circa 1970 (Box 4)
  - "How to be an Inventor," book proof, circa 1980; 2 (Box 4)
  - "How to Make Your Own Movies," book proofs, circa 1973 (Box 4)
  - "How to Ooze and other ways of Travelling," book proof, circa 1961 (Box 4)
  - "How to Run a Railroad," book proof (Box 4)
  - "Lens and Shutter," book proof, circa 1971 (Box 4)
  - "Little Bear," galley proof, circa 1957 (Box 9)
  - "Machines and How They Work," book proof, circa 1983 (Box 4)
  - "Maps: Getting from Here to There," book proof, circa 1991 (Box 4)
  - "Model Cars and Trucks and How to Build Them," book jacket, circa 1974 (Box 4)
  - "Olaf is Late," book proof, circa 1963 (Box 4)
  - "Paper, Ink and Roller," book proofs, circa 1958 (Box 4)
  - "Paul's Horse Herman," book proof, circa 1958 (Box 4)
  - "Pencil, Pen and Brush," book proof, circa 1961 (Box 4)
  - "Sailing Small Boats," book proof, circa 1967; 2 (Box 4)
  - "Ship Models and How to Build Them," book proof, circa 1973; 2 (Box 4)
  - "Something for Now, Something for Later," book proof, circa 1956 (Box 4)
  - "Sticks, Spools and Feathers," book proof, circa 1962 (Box 4)
  - "Submarines and Other Underwater Craft", circa 1990 (Box 4)
  - "True Book About Policemen, Etc.," galley proof (Box 4)
- Illustrated Journals, Series III
  - "Dirty Postcard Society", circa 2004 (Box 4)
  - "Fish Chicken", circa 1995 (Box 4)
  - "A Pustular Journal", circa 1989 (Box 4)
- Correspondence, Series IV
  - "3D Book" (Box 4)
  - Addison-Wesley Publishing Company, circa 1972-1981 (Box 4)
  - Aircraft - Houghton Contract, circa 1994 (Box 4)
  - California State Library, circa 1968 (Box 4)
  - "Carvings", circa 1974 (Box 4)
  - "Collage", circa 1967-1969 (Box 4)
  - Department of the Air Force, circa 1968 (Box 4)
  - Ford - Lockheed, circa 1968 (Box 4)
  - Great Northern, circa 1968 (Box 4)
  - Harper Collins, circa 1989-1992 (Box 4)
  - "How to be a Hero," children correspondence (Box 4)
  - Library of Congress and G. Eastman House photography, circa 1970-1971 (Box 4)
  - "Movies Research", circa 1972 (Box 4)
  - Nicholas Kayne - Edmund Ward Ltd., circa 1958-1970 (Box 4)
  - Office of the Secretery of Defense, folder (Box 5)
  - "Paint, Brush and Palette", circa 1966 (Box 5)
  - Photographers, circa 1970-1971 (Box 5)
  - "Print It", circa 1958 (Box 5)
  - Royalties (Box 5)
    - Addison-Wesley Royalties (Box 5)
    - Harper Collins Royalties, 3 (Box 5)
    - Houghton Mifflin Royalties, 3 (Box 5)
    - Miscellaneous Book Royalties (Box 5)
    - Royalty Statements, circa 1970s; 2 (Box 5)
  - Smithsonian - N.A.S.M. forms, 2 (Box 5)
  - Sources - cartoons (Rights and Permissions), circa 1988-1989 (Box 5)
- Other Papers, Series V
  - Memorial Program, circa 2007 (Box 5)
  - Miscellaneous material removed from Printed Items (Box 5)
  - "Silvermine Guild of Artists," poster (Box 5)
  - Stock Record Sheets (Box 5)
- Photographs, Series VI
  - Aircraft photocopies (Box 5)
  - Airforce, circa 1968 (Box 5)
  - American Museum of Natural History - "Milky Way Galaxy", circa 1968 (Box 5)
  - "Buildings," photographs, 3 (Box 9)
  - "Buildings," photographs, 2 (Box 10)
  - "Cars and Trucks" photograph discards (Box 5)
  - "Cars and Trucks" photograph discards (Box 11)
  - "Carving" photograph discards, 2 (Box 11)
  - Detroit Diesel Engine Division, circa 1968 (Box 5)
  - General Dynamics - Henry L. Stimson Submarine, circa 1968 (Box 5)
  - Hughes Aircraft, circa 1968 (Box 5)
  - "Left Over Photos - Model Planes" (Box 11)
  - "Locomotives" and "Military Aircraft" (Box 5)
  - "Martin Iger Photograph" (Box 11)
  - "Movies," photograph (Box 11)
  - Museum of Modern Art (Box 5)
  - NASA Rockets (Box 5)
  - Native American photographs (Box 5)
  - Negative (Box 5)
  - "Photos of Sculptures - Clay, W+W", 2 (Box 5)
  - "Photos of Sculptures - Clay, W+W" (Box 12)
  - "Plantation Owners, circa 1936," photographs (Box 12)
  - Skyscrapers, photographs (Box 5)
  - Smithsonian Institute - "Galaxy," photographs (Box 6)
  - "Trains," photographs (Box 6)
  - "Trains," photographs, 2 (Box 12)
  - "Train / Feet" photograph (Box 6)
  - Union Pacific Railroad, circa 1968 (Box 6)
  - U.S. Department of Interior (Box 6)
  - Various photographs, 6 (Box 6)
  - Various photographs, 2 (Box 12)
  - Various photographs, 3 (Box 13)
  - Westinghouse Electric Corporation (Box 6)
- Printed Material, Series VII
  - Adelphi University: Library Handbook of Information, circa 1978 (Box 6)
  - Adelphi University: Undergraduate Bulletin, circa 1887-1988 (Box 6)
  - Art in Children's Books, pamphlet, circa 1975 (Box 6)
  - Aspects of Book Collecting, circa 1977 (Box 6)
  - Authors Guild Bulletin, circa 1994-1996 (Box 6)
  - Delphian, newspaper, 1991 October 18 (Box 6)
  - Fifty Books of the Year - 1954: 33rd Annual Exhibition, circa 1955 (Box 6)
  - Fifty Books of the Year - 1955: 34th Annual Exhibition, circa 1956 (Box 6)
  - Hamilton Fraser Exhibition Catalog, circa 1960 (Box 6)
  - Hand Bookbinding: The Art and Craft, circa 1979 (Box 6)
  - "Harvey Weiss" book pamphlets, circa 1980 (Box 6)
  - Milton Avery Drawings, circa 1973 (Box 6)
  - North Light ...A Source Book For Artist, 1970 July (Box 6)
  - Sculptures 11, International Sculpture Conference packet, circa 1980 (Box 6)
  - Sculpture Exhibition, poster, circa 1972 (Box 6)
  - Selections from the Permant Collection of the Arkanas Arts Center Foundation, circa 1983 (Box 6)
  - "Some easy-to-make projects," poster (Box 6)
  - Young Scott Books catalogue (Box 6)
  - Beginning Artists Library: Teachers Manual, circa 1972 (Box 6)
- Book Art, Storyboards, and Oversize Photographs, Series VIII
  - "Horse in No Hurry," book art, circa 1961 (Box 7)
  - "Strange and Wonderful Aircraft," book art, circa 1995; 3 (Box 7)
  - "Strange and Wonderful Aircraft," book art, circa 1995; 4 (Box 8)
  - "Pencil, Pen and Brush - missing prints," storyboards (Box 8)
  - Miscellaneous Loose Material, book project (Box 14 (Oversize))
  - "Model Airplanes," book project (Box 15 (Oversize))
  - "Submarines," book project (Box 16 (Oversize))
  - "Black Stone Knife" and "Ne Knife," book art (Box 17 (Oversize))
  - "Building" and "Rubber Band and Donuts," book art (Box 18 (Oversize))
  - "Cartoons," book art (Box 19 (Oversize))
  - "The Lazy Day" mech., book art (Box 20 (Oversize))
  - "Machines and How They Work," book art (Box 21 (Oversize))
  - Putnam Production Department mech., book art (Box 22 (Oversize))
  - Trains, research material (Box 23 (Oversize))
  - Blade Stone and Doubleday, photographs (Box 24 (Oversize))
  - Black Stone and Doubleday, storyboard (Box 25 (Oversize))
  - "Cars and Trucks," photographs (Box 26 (Oversize))
  - "Carvings," photographs (Box 27 (Oversize))
  - "Carvings," photographs (Box 28 (Oversize))
  - "Carvings," photographs (Box 29 (Oversize))
  - "Carvings," storyboards (Box 30 (Oversize))
  - "Ceramics," photographs (Box 31 (Oversize))
  - "Ceramics," photographs (Box 32 (Oversize))
  - "Ceramics" (Not Used), photographs (Box 33 (Oversize))
  - "Clay", photographs (Box 34 (Oversize))
  - "Collage and Construction," photographs (Box 35 (Oversize))
  - "Collage and Construction," photographs (Box 36 (Oversize))
  - "Collage and Construction," storyboard (Box 37 (Oversize))
  - "How to Be an Inventor," photographs (Box 38 (Oversize))
  - "How to Be an Inventor," photographs (Box 39 (Oversize))
  - "Lens and Shutter - big pictures," photographs (Box 40 (Oversize))
  - "Movies," photographs (Box 41 (Oversize))
  - "Movies," photographs (Box 42 (Oversize))
  - "Movies," photographs (Box 43 (Oversize))
  - "Movies," photographs (Box 44 (Oversize))
  - "Movies," photographs (Box 45 (Oversize))
  - "Movies," photographs (Box 46 (Oversize))
  - "R.R.," photographs (Box 47 (Oversize))
  - "R.R.," photographs (Box 48 (Oversize))
  - "R.R.," photographs (Box 49 (Oversize))
  - "Sailing Small Boats," photographs (Box 50 (Oversize))
  - "Sailing Small Boats," storyboard (Box 51 (Oversize))
  - "Sticks, Spools and Feathers," photographs (Box 52 (Oversize))
  - "Sticks, Spools and Feathers," photographs (Box 53 (Oversize))
  - "Sticks, Spools and Feathers," storyboards (Box 54 (Oversize))
  - Young Scott "Lens and Shutter," photographs (Box 55 (Oversize))
  - Young Scott "Lens and Shutter," photographs (Box 56 (Oversize))
  - Young Scott "Lens and Shutter," photographs (Box 57 (Oversize))
  - Young Scott "Lens and Shutter," photographs (Box 58 (Oversize))
  - "1D, 2D, 3D," storyboards (Box 59 (Oversize))
  - "24 and Stanley," storyboards (Box 60 (Oversize))
  - Artwork various, storyboards (Box 61 (Oversize))
  - "Bridges," storyboards (Box 62 (Oversize))
  - "Bridges," storyboards (Box 63 (Oversize))
  - "Bridges," storyboards (Box 64 (Oversize))
  - "Cars and Trucks," storyboards (Box 65 (Oversize))
  - "Cars and Trucks," storyboards (Box 66 (Oversize))
  - "Cathedral," storyboards (Box 67 (Oversize))
  - "Clay W&W," storyboards (Box 68 (Oversize))
  - "Clay W&W," photographs (Box 69 (Oversize))
  - "Engines," storyboard (Box 70 (Oversize))
  - "Gadgets," storyboards (Box 71 (Oversize))
  - "Gondola for Fun," storyboards (Box 72 (Oversize))
  - "Hammer and Saw," storyboards (Box 73 (Oversize))
  - "Hammer and Saw," book projects (Box 74 (Oversize))
  - "Kenny's Monkey," storyboards (Box 75 (Oversize))
  - "Lens and Shutter," storyboards (Box 76 (Oversize))
  - "Map Mech.," storyboard (Box 77 (Oversize))
  - "Paint, Brush and Pencil," storyboard (Box 78 (Oversize))
  - "Paper, Ink and Roller," storyboard (Box 79 (Oversize))
  - "Paper, Ink and Roller" mech., storyboard (Box 80 (Oversize))
  - "Pencil, Paint and Brush," storyboard (Box 81 (Oversize))
  - "Pencil, Pen and Brush (Anatomy)," storyboard (Box 82 (Oversize))
  - "Pencil, Pen and Brush," storyboards (Box 83 (Oversize))
  - "Pencil, Pen and Brush," storyboards (Box 84 (Oversize))
  - "Sailing," storyboards (Box 85 (Oversize))
  - "Small Boats," storyboards (Box 86 (Oversize))
  - "Silly Sam, art and mech.," storyboards (Box 87 (Oversize))
  - "Sticks, Spools and Feathers," storyboard (Box 88 (Oversize))
  - "Time is When," storyboard (Box 89 (Oversize))
  - "Bridges," " Who," and "Ship Models," various (Box 90 (Oversize))
  - "Den" and Wm. R. Scott Inc., "Big Talk," various (Box 91 (Oversize))
  - "Go Fly a Kite," "Inventor," and "Magic Skipping," various (Box 92 (Oversize))
  - "Movies," "Olaf Reads," and "Wright Brothers," various (Box 93 (Oversize))
  - R.R. Jacket, True Book, Photos, Games and Puzzles, various (Box 94 (Oversize))
  - Teacher's Manual, Breakfast, Tools, Who, various (Box 95 (Oversize))
  - "Pencil, Brush and Pallette," book proof (Box 96 (Roll))